Guide to the Merton H. Miller Papers 1941-2002
University of Chicago Library
Miller, Merton H. Papers
1941-2002
61 linear feet (100 boxes)
Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Merton H. Miller was an economist, faculty member of the University of Chicago's Graduate School of Business, consultant, director of financial organizations, and free-market activist. Materials in this collection include drafts, publications, correspondence, research material, administrative records, and teaching material. This collection documents Miller's prolific writing and research, including his pioneering research in finance theory, for which he won the Nobel Prize in economics in 1990. Also included are records of his teaching and administrative activities at University of Chicago, speeches and public appearances, and work for professional organizations and corporations.
Information on Use
Access
Series III: Subseries 1: Sub-subseries 2 contains protected student information such as grade reports and graded student work. This material is restricted for 80 years.
Series III: Subseries 3: Sub-subseries 1 contains referee reports and letters of recommendation for colleagues. This material is restricted for 30 years. The restriction period for some files has expired; these files are open for research.
Series III: Subseries 3: Sub-subseries 2 contains letters of recommendation and other material related to the evaluation of students. This material is restricted for 80 years.
Series III: Subseries 4 contains University of Chicago administrative records. This material is restricted for 30 years. The restriction period for some files has expired; these files are open for research.
Series III: Subseries 6 contains videocassette tapes. Access to this material is restricted due to re-formatting and equipment requirements.
Series IV: Subseries 3 contains confidential legal and proprietary documents related to Miller's consulting work. This material is restricted indefinitely.
The remainder of the collection is open for research, with no restrictions.
Biographical Note
Merton Howard Miller (1923-2000) was an economist who won the Nobel Prize for his groundbreaking research in corporate finance. Born in Boston, Massachusetts, Miller attended Harvard University (A.B., 1944). In the mid- to late 1940s, Miller worked as an economist for the United States Treasury Department's Division of Tax Research, and the Division of Research and Statistics of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System. He earned a Ph.D. from Johns Hopkins University in 1952, mentored by Fritz Machlup.
After graduation from Johns Hopkins, Miller briefly held an appointment at the London School of Economics as an assistant lecturer in American economic history. In 1953, he moved on to the Carnegie Institute of Technology (now Carnegie-Mellon University), where he began working with Franco Modigliani on a series of papers on corporate finance. The two developed the Modigliani-Miller theorem, which holds that under certain assumptions the value of a firm is independent of the firm's ratio of debt to equity. The Modigliani-Miller theorem is now fundamental to thinking on capital structure.
In 1961, Miller accepted a position at the University of Chicago's Graduate School of Business. While continuing his collaborations with Modigliani, Miller taught business and finance courses, mentored students, served on administrative committees, and conducted further research in corporate finance. A prolific writer, he often collaborated with other researchers in economics and business, and was a lively and assertive debater.
In 1990, Miller's research with Franco Modigliani earned him the Nobel Prize in economics, which he shared with Harry Markowitz and William Sharpe.
Miller was active in professional organizations, serving as president of the American Finance Association, on the advisory and editorial boards of several academic publications and organizations. Late in his career, Miller consulted for banks and corporations, and held directorial positions at the Chicago Board of Trade and Chicago Mercantile Exchange. After his retirement, he described himself as a "professional keynote speaker," traveled worldwide to conferences, and spent time on his working farm in Woodstock, Illinois.
Scope Note
This collection documents Merton H. Miller's prolific career as an economist, teacher, consultant, director of financial organizations, and free-market activist. It also contains material broadly related to free-market economics and the Chicago school of economics.
The collection is organized into series to distinguish among different periods and facets of Miller's career.
Series I: Education and Early Career, contains material dating from Miller's studies at Harvard University and Johns Hopkins University, his work for the federal government, and his teaching at the London School of Economics. Materials found in this series span the years 1941-1943, and include notes, exams and papers for classes; a copy of his Ph.D. dissertation, reports, correspondence, and teaching materials such as lecture notes.
Series II: Carnegie Institute of Technology, documents Miller's research and teaching during the years 1954-1961. Drafts, correspondence, and research material related to Miller's foundational work with Franco Modigliani is found in this series.
Series III: University of Chicago, is the largest and most diverse series in the collection, documenting Miller's research, teaching and administrative work at the University. This series also contains material related to lectures, conferences and other non-University of Chicago events that Miller attended in his capacity as a faculty member. This series is divided into six subseries to distinguish among the types of material and levels of restriction included. Teaching material, research files, publications and drafts, correspondence, administrative records, and video recordings are included in this series.
Series IV: Consulting and Professional Activities, contains material related to Miller's activities outside of university teaching, research and speaking. These activities include participation in professional organizations; service on advisory, editorial and governing boards; and consulting for corporations and law firms. This series is divided into three subseries to distinguish among the types of material, and levels of organization and restriction. The material found in this series includes a large amount of proprietary and confidential information related to legal cases and corporate financing; it also includes correspondence, court documents, publications, drafts and administrative material.
Series V: Personal, is a small series containing copies of Miller's CV and list of publications, birthday party memorabilia, and material related to an alumni beer-tasting event.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Graduate School of Business. Records
Subject Headings
Miller, Merton H.; Modigliani, Franco; University of Chicago. Graduate School of Business; Finance; Chicago school of economics; Economists
INVENTORY
- Series I: Education and Early Career
  This series contains material dating from Miller's studies at Harvard University and Johns Hopkins University, his work for the federal government, and his teaching at the London School of Economics. Materials found in this series span the years 1941-1953, and include notes, exams and papers for classes; a copy of his Ph.D. dissertation, reports, correspondence, and teaching materials such as lecture notes.
  - Course notes, Harvard University, ca. 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - The Treatment of Capital Gains in the Federal Personal Income Tax, Harvard University, drafts, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - United States Treasury, Division of Tax Research, correspondence, reports and research material, 1942-1947 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, Division of Research and Statistics, correspondence, reports and research material, 1943-1956 (Box 2, Folder 5-9)
  - Tax return forms and course material on tax policy, 1943-1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Applications for federal employment, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Economics 201, History of Economic Thought, Johns Hopkins University, course material, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Economics 205, Johns Hopkins University, course material, ca. 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Economics 210, Johns Hopkins University, course material, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Math and Econometrics, Johns Hopkins University, course material, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - History of Modern Philosophy, Johns Hopkins University, course material, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fritz Machlup political economy classes, Johns Hopkins University, course material, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Johns Hopkins University, course material, ca. 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Teaching notes, ca. 1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Price Discrimination in the Railway Industry, Johns Hopkins University dissertation, photocopy, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - American economic history, London School of Economics, notecards, ca. 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - American economic history, London School of Economics, notecards, ca. 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - American economic history, London School of Economics, notes for Lectures 1-20, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
- Series II: Carnegie Institute of Technology
  This series documents Miller's research and teaching during the years 1954-1961. Drafts, correspondence, and research material related to Miller's foundational work with Franco Modigliani is found in this series. A small amount of administrative correspondence, including negotiations for Miller's move to the University of Chicago, is also included. Additional material related to the Modigliani-Miller theorems is found in Series III. Other reprints, drafts, research material and correspondence are also included in Series II.
  - "Decreasing Average Cost and the Theory of Railroad Rates," 1955, correspondence and drafts, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "The Cost of Capital, Corporation Finance and Keynesian Economics" (with Franco Modigliani), 1958, preliminary version of paper for Econometric Society, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Gregory C. Chow, correspondence and draft, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Martin Shubik and Gerald L. Thompson, "Games of Economic Survival," draft, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Research with Franco Modigliani on capital structure, 1957-1964 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Portfolio selection, offprints and notes, 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Review of Portfolio Selection, by Harry M. Markowitz, correspondence and drafts, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  - McKinsey Foundation Award, correspondence, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "Corporation Income Tax and Corporate Financial Policies," report to the Commission on Money and Credit, drafts, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
  - "Dividend Policy, Growth Opportunities and the Valuation of Shares" (with Franco Modigliani), 1961, correspondence and drafts, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
  - "Dividend Policy, Growth Opportunities and the Valuation of Shares" (with Franco Modigliani), 1961 correspondence and drafts, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Leverage, Dividend Policy and the Cost of Capital" (with Franco Modigliani), offprint and correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Franco Modigliani, correspondence, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bank reserves, publications, 1953-1961 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - James W. Lorie, correspondence, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - G.L. Bach, acceptance of Miller's resignation from faculty, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series III: University of Chicago
  This series documents Miller's research, teaching and administrative work at the University of Chicago, as well as material related to lectures, conferences and other non-University events that Miller attended in his capacity as a faculty member. This series is divided into six subseries to distinguish among types of material and levels of restriction.
  Series III: Subseries 1: Teaching Material, contains material related to courses taught by Miller, business courses, some of which Miller taught for several decades, as well as material for symposia, seminars and other advanced academic courses. This subseries is divided into two sub-subseries to distinguish between open and unrestricted papers: Sub-subseries 1: General, contains material such as syllabi, reading lists, and lecture notes. The files in Sub-subseries 2: Restricted, also contain grade reports, evaluated student work, letters of recommendation, and other protected student information.
  Series III: Subseries 2: Writing and Research, contains drafts, publications, notes, correspondence and other material related to Miller's academic research and prolific writing of articles, books, and speeches. Represented here are published and unpublished work from the 1960s-2000s. Files are organized according to topic or title when identified. Publication dates and names of co-authors are also given when available. Miller also filed drafts according to the location in which a speech was given, or by general topic.
  Series III: Subseries 3: Correspondence, contains letters and memoranda related to Miller's work in research, writing, teaching and publishing. Additional correspondence is found throughout the collection; the material included in this subseries includes material maintained by Miller specifically as correspondence files. This subseries is divided into two sub-subseries to distinguish between types of organization and levels of restriction. Sub-subseries 1: Subject file, includes correspondence from the 1960s-2000s, and is arranged alphabetically; it is important to note that the subjects described do not always identify the correspondents, but the individuals or organizations discussed. Referee reports and administrative correspondence are found in this sub-subseries, and are subject to restriction. Sub-subseries 2: Chronological File, also spans the 1960s-2000s. This series contains recommendations and other protected student information that is subject to restriction.
  Series III: Subseries 4: Administration, includes correspondence, reports, curriculum and programming material, and other documents related to Miller's service on a variety of university committees and administrative projects. Many of these administrative activities relate to tenure and appointment procedures. This series contains letters of recommendation, tenure review material, budget material, and other administrative records that are subject to restriction.
  Series III: Subseries 5: Arrangements for Speaking Engagements, is arranged chronologically and contains routine organizational material such as itineraries, reservation confirmations, letters of invitation, and expense reports. Some material on conference proceedings, such as schedules and programs, is also included. This subseries does not contain drafts, research material, or other substantial documents related to Miller's speeches and presentations - this material is found in Subseries 2.
  Series III: Subseries 6: Video Recordings, contains VHS cassette tapes of television broadcasts, conference proceedings, and press conferences in which Miller participated.
  - Subseries 1: Teaching Material
    - Sub-subseries 1: General
      - Business 303, 1969-1972 (Box 7, Folder 7-11)
      - Business 330, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Business 331, ca. 1973 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Business 333, 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 3-6)
      - Business 333, 1971-1987 (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
      - Business 333, 1980s (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
      - Business 437, Selected Topics in Corporate Finance, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
      - Business 438, Special Topics in Finance, 1986-1989 (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
      - Business 438, Special Topics in Finance, 1989-1993 (Box 12, Folder 1-6)
      - Business 438, Special Topics in Finance, 1990-1992 (Box 13, Folder 1-10)
      - Business 438, Special Topics in Finance, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
      - Business 538, 1996-1999 (Box 14, Folder 4-6)
      - Executive Program in Finance, 42nd-43rd Group, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Symposium on Financial Regulation, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Ph.D. examination in finance, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Exams, 1967-1988 (Box 15, Folder 2-6)
      - Course material, 1967-1982 (Box 15, Folder 7-10)
      - Course material, ca. 1970s-1993 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Restricted
      - Course material, ca. 1970s-1990s (Box 17, Folder 1-12)
      - Course material, ca. 1970s-1990s (Box 18, Folder 1-20)
      - Course material, ca. 1970s-1990 (Box 19, Folder 1-20)
  - Subseries 2: Writing and Research
    - Fritz Machlup, Essays in Economic Semantics, Merton H. Miller, ed., 1963, drafts and correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - "Dividend Policy and Market Valuation, A Reply" (with Franco Modigliani), 1963, drafts and correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - "Taxes and the Cost of Capital, A Correction" (with Franco Modigliani), 1963, drafts, notes and correspondence, ca. 1963 (Box 20, Folder 3-4)
    - Modigliani-Miller research, notes, drafts, correspondence and publications, ca. 1960-1964 (Box 20, Folder 5-6)
    - Modigliani-Miller research, notes, drafts, correspondence and publications, ca. 1960-1964 (Box 21, Folder 1-5)
    - Modigliani-Miller research, notes, drafts, correspondence and publications, ca. 1960-1964 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
    - "Herbert A. Simon," presentation statement for honorary degree, drafts and correspondence, 1963 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Speech draft, Management Conference, 1963 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - "General Equilibrium of the Capital Markets under Uncertainty" (with Franco Modigliani), drafts, correspondence and research material, 1960-1966 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - "Some Estimates of the Cost of Capital in the Electric Utility Industry" (with Franco Modigliani), 1966, drafts and correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 22, Folder 6-8)
    - "A Model of the Demand for Money by Firms" (with Daniel Orr), 1966, drafts, correspondence and research material, 1956-1967 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - "A Model of the Demand for Money by Firms" (with Daniel Orr), 1966, drafts, correspondence and research material, 1956-1967 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - "Franco Modigliani," honorary degree presentation, speech drafts and correspondence, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Joseph E. Stiglitz, draft, correspondence and administrative material, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - "Reply to Heinz and Sprenkle" (with Franco Modigliani), 1969, drafts and correspondence, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - "The Effects of an Improved Option Market on the Costs of Debt and of Equity Capital," drafts, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Time series, notes, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Michael C. Jensen, drafts and correspondence, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Eugene F. Fama, drafts, ca. 1960s (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Dale W. Jorgenson, draft, ca. 196 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Drafts, correspondence and research material, 1964-1969 (Box 23, Folder 10-13)
    - Refunding model, notes, ca. 1960s (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Capital theory and capital budgets, notes, ca. 1960s (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Notes and drafts, ca. 1960s (Box 24, Folder 3-6)
    - Chicago Board of Trade study of put and call options, correspondence, drafts and research material, 1968-1970 (Box 24, Folder 7-9)
    - Chicago Board of Trade study of put and call options, correspondence, drafts and research material, 1968-1970 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - NASDAQ research material, 1969-1971 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - "Rates of Return in Relation to Risk, A Reexamination of Some Recent Findings" (with Myron S. Scholes), 1972, drafts, research material and correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 25, Folder 3-9)
    - "Rates of Return in Relation to Risk, A Reexamination of Some Recent Findings" (with Myron S. Scholes), 1972, drafts, research material and correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 26, Folder 1-5)
    - "Comments on 'Money and Stock Prices, The Channels of Influence,' by Michael J. Hamburger and Levis A. Kochin," presented at the American Financial Association meeting, 1971, drafts and notes, 1971-1972 (Box 26, Folder 7-8)
    - "The Fine Art of Agenda Positioning," draft, ca. 1970 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Jacques Drèze, research material, ca. 1970 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Vernon L. Smith, drafts, ca. 1970s (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Business simulation games, research material, ca. 1970 (Box 27, Folder 4-5)
    - "Quantitative Methods in Business," drafts, ca. 1970 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Robert J. Barro and Daniel Orr, cash management and demand for money, drafts, ca. 1970 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Corporate cash balance models, notes, ca. 1970 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Strikes, research material, ca. 1970 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - The Theory of Finance (with Eugene F. Fama), 1972, drafts and notes, 1968-1973 (Box 27, Folder 10-14)
    - The Theory of Finance (with Eugene F. Fama), 1972, drafts and notes, 1968-1973 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - "An Analytical Model of Energy and the Economy" (with E.M. Bohn and Charles W. Upton), drafts, meeting minutes and grant proposal, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Demand for money, notes and research material, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - "Informational Content of Dividend Changes" (with Myron Scholes), drafts, notes and research material, ca. 1974 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - "Comments by Merton H. Miller on 'Permanent and Transitory Income Effects in a Model of Optimal Consumption with Wage Income Uncertainty,' by David Sibley," presented at the Bell Laboratories Symposium on the Economics of Uncertainty, 1974, drafts and conference material, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 5-6)
    - James Scott, drafts, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - James D. Macbeth, draft, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Macroeconomics, a Neoclassical Introduction (with Charles W. Upton), 1974, drafts and notes, ca. 1971 (Box 29, Folder 1-5)
    - Talks presented at Recent Developments in Applied Economics, 1975, drafts, research material and conference program, 1974-1975 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - "Some Estimates of Arrow-Debreu Prices on State-Contingent Claims" (with R. Ibbotson), drafts, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Talk presented at Financial Decision-Making under Uncertainty, Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 1975, drafts, correspondence and conference material, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - "Leasing, Buying and the Cost of Capital Services" (with Charles W. Upton), 1976, drafts, correspondence and research material, 1962-1975 (Box 29, Folder 9-10)
    - "Leasing, Buying and the Cost of Capital Services" (with Charles W. Upton), 1976, drafts, correspondence and research material, 1962-1975 (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
    - Option theory, research material and notes, 1975-1976 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Referee reports and reviews, 1975-1977 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - States model, notes and research material, 1975-1976 (Box 30, Folder 6-9)
    - "Debt and Taxes" presidential address presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Finance Association, 1976, drafts, notes and research material, 1975-1976 (Box 31, Folder 1-3)
    - "Commentary on Financial Markets, Default and Bankruptcy, the Role of the State," presented at the Liberty Fund, Inc. Seminar on the Economics of Bankruptcy, University of Miami School of Law, 1977, drafts, research material and conference material, 1976-1978 (Box 31, Folder 4-7)
    - "Note on the ITC," draft, 1977 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - "Some Estimates of Arrow-Debreu Prices for State-Contingent Claims" (with Rolf Banz), presented at the Finance Workshop, Dartmouth College, 1977, drafts and research material, 1977 (Box 31, Folder 9)